In the last video, we talked
前回のビデオでは
about the Gaussian distribution. In
ガウス分布について話した。
this video lets apply that
今回のビデオではそれを用いて
to develop an anomaly detection algorithm.
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムを開発する。
Let's say that we have an
ラベル付けされていない
unlabeled training set of M
m個の手本があるとしよう。
examples, and each of
これらの手本の個々は
these examples is going to
R nに属するフィーチャーと
be a feature in Rn so
なっている。
your training set could be,
つまりトレーニングセットは例えば
feature vectors from the last
製造した直近m個の
M aircraft engines being manufactured.
航空機エンジンのフィーチャーベクトルでも良し、
Or it could be features from m
m人のユーザーのフィーチャーでも
users or something else.
それ以外の何かでも良い。
The way we are going to address
アノマリー検出に
anomaly detection, is we are
どうアプローチしていくか、というと、
going to model p of x
データセットからp(x)を
from the data sets.
モデリングしていきます。
We're going to try to figure out what are high probability features, what
どんなフィーチャーの組みの確率が高くてどんなフィーチャーの組みが低い確率なのかを
are lower probability types of features.
見つけ出したい。
So, x is a
で、xはベクトルなので、
vector and what we
p(x)をモデリングするとは
are going to do is model p of
x1の確率、、、ここで
x, as probability of x1,
x1はxの最初の成分ですが、
that is of the first component
x1の確率に、
of x, times the probability
掛けることのx2となる確率、
of x2, that is the probability
これは二番目のフィーチャーの確率で、
of the second feature, times the
それに掛けることの
probability of the third
三番目のフィーチャーの確率、
feature, and so on up
などなどと、
to the probability of the final feature
最後のフィーチャーxnの確率まで
of Xn.
掛け合わせます。
Now I'm leaving space here cause I'll fill in something in a minute.
ここにスペースを空けたのは、あとでここに書きたい事があるからです。
So, how do we
で、これらの個々の項、
model each of these terms,
p(x1)、p(x2)などを
p of X1, p of X2, and so on.
どうモデリングするのでしょうか？
What we're going to do,
どうやるかというと、
is assume that the feature,
x1がガウス分布に従って
X1, is distributed according
分布していると
to a Gaussian distribution, with
想定します、なんらかの平均、
some mean, which you
それをミュー1と
want to write as mu1 and
書きましょう、
some variance, which I'm going
そしてなんらかの分散、
to write as sigma squared 1,
それをシグマ二乗の1と書くことにしましょう。
and so p of X1 is
そしてp(x1)は
going to be a Gaussian
平均がミュー1で
probability distribution, with mean
分散シグマ二乗1の
mu1 and variance sigma squared 1.
ガウスの確率分布に従うとする。
And similarly I'm
同様に
going to assume that X2
x2はガウス分布に従って分布していると、、、
is distributed, Gaussian,
ところで、
that's what this little tilda stands for,
この小さなチルダ記号は
that means distributed Gaussian
（右辺に従い）分布している、という事を意味する。
with mean mu2 and Sigma
で、平均がミュー2で分散がシグマ二乗の2の
squared 2, so it's distributed according
ガウス分布に従っている、つまり異なるガウス分布に従って
to a different Gaussian, which has
分布している、と想定する。
a different set of parameters, mu2 sigma square 2.
それは異なるパラメータのセット、ミュー2とシグマ二乗の2を持っている。
And similarly, you know,
同様に、
X3 is yet another
x3もまた別のガウス分布で、
Gaussian, so this
これもまた
can have a different mean and
他のフィーチャーとは異なる
a different standard deviation than the
平均と標準偏差を持ちえる。
other features, and so on, up to XN.
などなどと、xnまで続く。
And so that's my model.
以上が私のモデルとなる。
Just as a side comment for
あなたたちの中のうち、
those of you that are experts in
統計のスペシャリストの人向けの余談ですが、
statistics, it turns out that
私の書き下した方程式の
this equation that I just
実際にはフィーチャーの値、
wrote out actually corresponds to an
x1からxnまでの値が
independence assumption on the
独立である事を
values of the features x1 through xn.
仮定している。
But in practice it turns out
だが実際には、
that the algorithm of this fragment, it works just fine,
ここに書いたアルゴリズム片は、
whether or not these features are
これらのフィーチャーが
anywhere close to independent and
独立に近いかどうかに関わらず機能する、
even if independence assumption doesn't
実は独立の仮定が成り立たない時ですら
hold true this algorithm works just fine.
このアルゴリズムはうまく機能する。
But in case you don't know
だけどもしあなたが、たった今、私が使った
those terms I just used independence assumptions and so on,
独立の仮定だとかの用語の意味が分からなければ
don't worry about it.
気にしないでよろしい。
You'll be able to understand
そのうち分かるようになるだろうし、
it and implement this algorithm just fine
このアルゴリズムは正しく実装出来るだろうから。
and that comment was really meant only for the experts in statistics.
さきのコメントは単に統計の専門家向けのコメントに過ぎない。
Finally, in order to
最後に、これのまとめとして、
wrap this up, let me
この式を
take this expression and write it a little bit more compactly.
もうちょっとだけコンパクトに書く。
So, we're going to
これを、以下のように
write this is a product
jが1からnまでの
from J equals one
以下のpの積として書くことにする。
through N, of P
pのxjで、xjは
of XJ parameterized by
ミューjとシグマ二乗jで
mu j comma sigma squared
パラメトライズされている。
j. So this funny
つまりこのファニーな
symbol here, there is
記号、大文字の
capital Greek alphabet pi,
ギリシャ文字のアルファベット、パイだが、
that funny symbol there corresponds to
そのファニーな記号は、値の集合に対して
taking the product of a set of values.
積をとる事に対応する。
And so, you're familiar with
つまり、和の記号に
the summation notation, so the
慣れているなら、
sum from i equals one through
iを1からnまでのiの
n, of i. This
和を取ると、
means 1 + 2 + 3 plus
この意味は1+2+3+...
dot dot dot, up to
とnまでの和という意味。
n. Where as this
一方このファニーな
funny symbol here, this product
記号は、この掛け算記号は、
symbol, right product from i
iが1からnまでの
equals 1 through n
iの掛け算。
of i.  Then this
これの意味する所は
means that, it's just like summation except that we're now multiplying.
和の記号とほとんど同じだけど、今回は足す代わりに掛け算する、という意味。
This becomes 1 times
これは結局、1掛ける
2 times 3 times up
2掛ける3掛ける、、、と、nまで掛ける。
to N. And so using
で、この積の記法を
this product notation, this
使うと、
product from j equals 1 through n of this expression.
このjが1からnまでこの式を掛け合わせる、というのを使うと
It's just more compact, it's
もっとコンパクトになる。
just shorter way for writing
これらの項全部を
out this product of
書く、より短い
of all of these terms up there.
方法となるワケ。
Since we're are taking these p
だってこれらのpの、ミューjとシグマjが
of x j given mu j
与えられた時のxjの
comma sigma squared j terms
値をとって、
and multiplying them together.
それらを掛け合わせているのだから。
And, by the way the problem
ところで、このpのxという
of estimating this distribution
分布を推計する問題は
p of x, they're sometimes called
密度推計の問題、と
the problem of density estimation.
呼ばれる事がある。
Hence the title of the slide.
それがこのスライドのタイトルでもある。
So putting everything together, here
では、全部合わせると、
is our anomaly detection algorithm.
我らのアノマリー検出のアルゴリズムはこうなる。
The first step is to choose
最初のステップはフィーチャーを選ぶ事、
features, or come up with
または見つけ出すことだ、
features xi that we think
アノマリーであるサンプルを示してくれると
might be indicative of anomalous examples.
思われるようなフィーチャーxiを。
So what I mean by that,
つまり、どういう意味かというと、
is, try to come
以下のようなフィーチャーを
up with features, so that when there's
探し出すという事です: あなたのシステムに
an unusual user in your
詐欺行為を働いているかもしれない
system that may be doing
普通でないユーザーが
fraudulent things, or when the
いた時に、または航空機エンジンの
aircraft engine examples, you know
例では、何かおかしな事、
there's something funny, something strange about one of the aircraft engines.
何か奇妙な事が航空機エンジンに起こっている時には
Choose features X I, that
普通でないほど大きな値、
you think might take on unusually
または普通でないほど小さな値をとる、と
large values, or unusually
あなたが思うようなフィーチャーxiを選ぶ、
small values, for what an
アノマリーのサンプルが
anomalous example might look like.
どんな感じかを知る為に。
But more generally, just try
またはより一般的に、
to choose features that describe general
集めているデータの対象の一般的な性質を
properties of the things that you're collecting data on.
良くとらえているフィーチャーを集めても良い。
Next, given a training set,
次に、得られたm個のトレーニングセットに対し、
of M, unlabled examples,
ラベル無し手本に対し、
X1 through X M, we
x1からxmまでに対し、
then fit the parameters,
パラメータをフィットさせる、
mu 1 through mu n, and
ミュー1からミューnまでと、
sigma squared 1 through sigma
シグマ二乗の1からシグマ二乗のnまで。
squared n, and so these
これらの式は
were the formulas similar to
前回のビデオでやった
the formulas we have
式と似ている。
in the previous video, that we're
これらのパラメータの推計に
going to use the estimate
この式を使っていく。
each of these parameters, and just to give
いくつか解釈を与えておくと、
some interpretation, mu J,
ミューj、
that's my average value of the j feature.
これはフィーチャーjの平均だ。
Mu j goes in this term p of xj.
そしてこのミューjはpのxjの式に
which is parametrized by mu J
パラメータとして入る、それは
and sigma squared J. And
ミューjとシグマ二乗jでパラメトライズされていたのだった。
so this says for the
だからこれの言ってる事は
mu J just take the
ミューjは単に
mean over my training
トレーニングセットに渡って
set of the values of the j feature.
フィーチャーjの平均を取った物、という事。
And, just to mention, that you
そして補足しておくと、
do this, you compute these
あなたは、これらの式を
formulas for j equals
jが1からnまでに渡って
one through n. So use
計算することになる。
these formulas to estimate mu
つまりこれらの式を使ってミュー1、
1, to estimate mu
ミュー2、と
2, and so on up to
ミューnまで、推計する。
mu n, and similarly for sigma
シグマ二乗も同様だ。
squared, and it's also
そしてまた、これらの
possible to come up with vectorized versions of these.
ベクトル化したバージョンを作る事も可能だ。
So if you think of
ミューをベクトルとして
mu as a vector, so mu
考えると、
if is a vector there's mu 1,
つまりミュー1があって、
mu 2, down to mu
ミュー2があって、、、と
n, then a vectorized
ミューnまで。すると
version of that set
ベクトル化したバージョンの
of parameters can be written
パラメータのセットは
like so sum from 1
1からnまでの
equals one through n xi.
xiの和と書ける。
So, this formula that I
つまり今書いたこの式で
just wrote out estimates this
このxiをフィーチャーベクトルとして
xi as the feature vectors
n個全てのミューの値を
that estimates mu for all the values of n simultaneously.
同時に推計する。
And it's also possible to come
そしてまた、シグマ二乗jの
up with a vectorized formula for
推計についても
estimating sigma squared j. Finally,
ベクトル化した式を作れる。
when you're given a new example, so
最後に、新しいサンプルを与えられたら、
when you have a new aircraft engine
つまり、新しい航空エンジンが来て、
and you want to know is this aircraft engine anomalous.
この航空機エンジンがアノマリーなのかどうかを知りたいとすると、
What we need to do is then
やらなくてはならない事は
compute p of x, what's the probability of this new example?
p(x)を、この新しいエンジンの確率を計算する事だ。
So, p of x is equal
で、p(x)は
to this product, and
この積と等しくて、
what you implement, what you compute,
実装としては、計算するのは、
is this formula and
この式で、
where over here, this thing
ここにある、これは
here this is just the
ガウス確率の
formula for the Gaussian
式だ。
probability, so you compute
だからこれを計算し、
this thing, and finally if
最終的に、この確率が
this probability is very small,
とても小さければ、
then you flag this thing as an anomaly.
これをアノマリーとフラグづけする。
Here's an example of an application of this method.
これはこの手法の適用例だ。
Let's say we have this data
このスライドの左上に
set plotted on the upper left of this slide.
プロットしたようなデータがあるとしよう。
if you look at this, well, lets look the feature of x1.
もしこの、フィーチャーx1を見てみると、
If you look at this data set, it
もしこのデータセットを見てみると、
looks like on average, the features
見た感じだいたい
x1 has a mean of about 5
フィーチャーx1の平均は5のあたりで、
and the standard deviation, if
標準偏差は
you only look at just the x1
このデータセットのx1の値だけを
values of this data set
見ると、標準偏差は
has the standard deviation of maybe 2.
だいたい2くらい。
So that sigma 1 and
つまりそれがシグマ1。
looks like x2 the
そしてフィーチャーx2の
values of the features as
値を見ると、
measured on the vertical axis,
それは縦軸で測れて
looks like it has an average
その平均は見たところ
value of about 3, and
だいたい3くらいで、
a standard deviation of about 1. So if
標準偏差はだいたい1。
you take this data set and if
だからこのデータセットに対して
you estimate mu1, mu2, sigma1,
ミュー1、ミュー2と、シグマ1、シグマ2を
sigma2, this is what you get.
推計すると、これが得られる物だ。
And again, I'm writing sigma here,
ここでもまた、シグマとここに書いた。
I'm think about standard deviations, but
標準偏差について考えているけれど、
the formula on the previous 5
前のスライドの式は
actually gave the estimates of the squares
これらの二乗の推計を与える物だった。
of theses things, so sigma squared 1 and sigma squared 2.
つまりシグマ二乗の1、シグマ二乗の2。
So, just be careful whether
だから、シグマ1とシグマ2を使ってるのか
you are using sigma 1, sigma
それともシグマ二乗1とシグマ二乗2を
2, or sigma squared 1 or sigma squared 2.
使ってるのかに、注意しなさい。
So, sigma squared 1 of course
そしてシグマ二乗1はもちろん、
would be equal to 4, for
イコール4となる。
example, as the square of 2.
2の二乗だから。
And in pictures what p of
図では、 ミュー1とシグマ二乗1で
x1 parametrized by mu1 and
パラメトライズされている
sigma squared 1 and p
p(x1)と、
of x2, parametrized by mu
ミュー2とシグマ二乗2で
2 and sigma squared 2, that
パラメトライズされたp(x2)は
would look like these two distributions over here.
ここにあるこれら2つの分布のような見た目となるだろう。
And, turns out that
そして結局、
if were to plot of p
p(x)をプロットすると
of x, right, which
それはこれら2つの
is the product of these two
積だったのだから
things, you can actually get
実際にはこんな感じの
a surface plot that looks like this.
平面プロットが得られる。
This is a plot of p
これはp(x)のプロットで
of x, where the height
その高さ、
above of this, where the
この上の高さ、
height of this surface at
平面上のある特定の点の
a particular point, so given a
高さは、つまりある
particular x1 x2
x1、x2が与えられた時に
values of x2 if
x2の値が2で
x1 equals 2, x equal 2, that's this point.
x1の値が2なら、この点だ。
And the height of this 3-D
そしてこの三次元平面の高さが
surface here, that's p
それこそがp(x)だ。
of x. So p of x, that is the height
つまりp(x)、それがこのプロットの
of this plot, is
高さだ。
literally just p of x1
それは文字通りミュー1とシグマ二乗1で
parametrized by mu 1 sigma
パラメトライズされたp(x1)
squared 1, times p
掛けることの
of x2 parametrized by
ミュー2とシグマ二乗2で
mu 2 sigma squared 2.
パラメトライズされたp(x2)である。
Now, so this is
つまり、これがパラメータを
how we fit the parameters to this data.
このデータにフィットさせる方法だ。
Let's see if we have a couple of new examples.
新しいサンプルが幾つか来た場合を考えてみよう。
Maybe I have a new example there.
新しいサンプルはここかもしれない。
Is this an anomaly or not?
これはアノマリーか？そうでないか？
Or, maybe I have a different
また、それとは別のサンプルが、
example, maybe I have a different second example over there.
例えば二番目のサンプルがここにあるとしよう。
So, is that an anomaly or not?
これはアノマリーか？そうでないか？
They way we do that is, we
それを区別する方法は
would set some value for
ある値エプシロンをセットする、
Epsilon, let's say I've chosen
ここではエプシロンを
Epsilon equals 0.02.
0.02としたとしよう。
I'll say later how we choose Epsilon.
どうやってエプシロンを選ぶかは後で話す。
But let's take this first
まずは最初のサンプルを
example, let me call this
取ってみよう。このサンプルを
example X1 test.
x1 test と呼ぶ事にする。
And let me call the second example
そして二番目のサンプルをx2 testと
X2 test.
呼ぶことにする。
What we do is, we
で、どうするかというと、
then compute p of
p(x1 test)を計算する。
X1 test, so we use
その為に、この式を使って
this formula to compute it and
それを計算する。
this looks like a pretty large value.
これは見たところかなり大きな値に見える。
In particular, this is greater
特に、これはエプシロン
than, or greater than or equal to epsilon.
以上となっている。
And so this is a pretty
だからこれは、きわめて大きい確率で
high probability at least bigger
少なくともエプシロンより大きいとは言える。
than epsilon, so we'll say that
だからx1 testはアノマリーでは無い、と
X1 test is not an anomaly.
言って良かろう。
Whereas, if you compute p of
一方 p(x2 test) を計算してみると、
X2 test, well that is just a much smaller value.
これはもっとずっと小さい値となる。
So this is less than
これはエプシロンより小さい。
epsilon and so we'll say
だから、これは確かに
that that is indeed an anomaly,
アノマリーだと言える。
because it is much smaller than that epsilon that we then chose.
何故ならそれは、我らが選んだエプシロンより小さいから。
And in fact, I'd improve it here.
そして実際、ここで言った事は、
What this is really saying is that, you look through the 3d surface plot.
これの本当に意味している事は、三次元での表面プロットを見ると、
It's saying that all the
それの言わんとしている事は、
values of x1 and x2
その点の上の
that have a high height
表面までの高さが高い点となるx1，x2は、全て
above the surface, corresponds to
非アノマリーのサンプルに、つまりOKというかノーマルなサンプルに
an a non-anomalous example of an OK or normal example.
対応しているという事。
Whereas all the points far out
一方、遥か離れたこの辺の点は全て
here, all the points out
遥か離れたこの辺の点は全て、
here, all of those
これらの点は全て
points have very low
とても低い確率となっている。
probability, so we are
つまり、我らとしては、
going to flag those points
これらの点をアノマリーと
as anomalous, and so it's gonna define
フラグづけする事になる。つまりある領域を
some region, that maybe looks
それはこんな感じとなるだろうが、
like this, so that everything
その外の全ての点を
outside this, it flags
アノマリーとフラグづけ
as anomalous,
する事となる。
whereas the things inside this
一方で、このエプシロンの内部に
ellipse I just drew, if it
ある物たちは、ここに書いたように、
considers okay, or non-anomalous, not anomalous examples.
これはOK、または非アノマリーなサンプルとみなす。
And so this example x2
つまりこのサンプルx2 testは
test lies outside
その領域の外に位置しているので
that region, and so it
つまりそれはとても低い
has very small probability, and so we consider it an anomalous example.
確率なので、それはアノマリーのサンプルとみなす訳だ。
In this video we talked about how to
このビデオでは、どうやってp(x)を推計するかを
estimate p of x, the probability of
議論してきた。xとなる確率を。
x, for the purpose of
アノマリー検出のアルゴリズムを
developing an anomaly detection algorithm.
開発する為に。
And in this video, we also
そしてこのビデオではまた、
stepped through an entire process
所与のデータセットに対して
of giving data set, we
パラメータをフィッティングする、
have, fitting the parameters, doing parameter estimations.
パラメータを推計する全体の手順も見ていった。
We get mu and sigma parameters, and
パラメータであるミューとシグマを取得して、
then taking new examples and deciding
次に新しいサンプルに対して
if the new examples are anomalous or not.
それがアノマリーかどうかを判断した。
In the next few videos we
次のビデオでは、
will delve deeper into this algorithm,
このアルゴリズムに対してより深く見ていく。
and talk a bit more
そしてこれを実際にうまく運用する為に
about how to actually get this to work well.
ちょっとした補足の話もしていく。